# Pedro E. Harunari

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER · STATISTICAL PHYSICS

Department of Physics and Materials Science, University of Luxembourg, Campus Limpertsberg, 162a avenue de la Faïencerie, L-1511 Luxembourg (G. D. Luxembourg)

### **Personal Profile**

I am a postdoctoral researcher at the University of Luxembourg under the supervision of Prof. Massimiliano Esposito. My Ph.D. in physics was obtained from the University of São Paulo, Brazil, where intensive research and teaching activities were developed. I am an active researcher in statistical physics; my main goal is to understand and tame fluctuations in systems out of thermal equilibrium, alongside their thermodynamic properties. In particular, I investigate systems undergoing phase transitions, heat engines, stochastic thermodynamics, coarse-graining, applications to biophysics and chemistry, and the interplays between them.

### Education

#### **University of Luxembourg**

Luxembourg, Luxembourg

Dec 2022 - Current

Postdoctoral researcher

- Member of the group Complex Systems and Statistical Mechanics
- · Supervised by Prof. Massimiliano Esposito

University of São Paulo

São Paulo, Brazil

- **Doctorate in Physics** Mar 2018 - Nov 2022
- Thesis: "The role of time in nonequilibrium: transition-based coarse-graining, phase transitions and heat engines" DOI:10.11606/T.43.2022.tde-14122022-084103
- · Allowed to join the program without a Master's degree
- · Approved with the highest grades in every course
- · Teaching assistant experience during three semesters, both in graduate and undergraduate levels

**University of São Paulo** São Paulo, Brazil

Bachelor in Physics

Feb 2014 - Nov 2017

- 1.5 years of research training activities
- · One semester as teaching assistant
- Complementary courses at: IMPA, CBPF and ICTP-SAIFR

## **List of Publications**

8 articles published in internationally renowned journals and one preprint.

From Google Scholar: 101 citations, h-index 6.

•	PE Harunari, A Garilli, and M Polettini, "The beat of a current"	
	arXiv preprint arXiv:2205.05060, submitted for publication	2022
•	PE Harunari, A Dutta, M Polettini, and E Roldán, "What to learn from a few visible transitions' statistics?"	
	Physical Review X 12, 041026	2022
•	IN Mamede, PE Harunari, BAN Akasaki, K Proesmans, and CE Fiore, "Obtaining efficient thermal engines from	
	interacting Brownian particles under time-periodic drivings"	
	Physical Review E <b>105</b> (2), 024106	2022
•	CE Fiore, PE Harunari, CEF Noa, and GT Landi, "Current fluctuations in nonequilibrium discontinuous phase transitions"	
	Physical Review E <b>104</b> (6), 064123	2021
•	PE Harunari, S Fernando Filho, CE Fiore, and A Rosas, "Maximal power for heat engines: Role of asymmetric	
	interaction times"	
	Physical Review Research 3 (2), 023194	2021
•	PE Harunari, CE Fiore, and K Proesmans, "Exact statistics and thermodynamic uncertainty relations for a periodically driven electron pump"	
	Journal of Physics A: Mathematical and Theoretical 53 (37), 374001	2020
•	CEF Noa, PE Harunari, MJ de Oliveira, and CE Fiore, "Entropy production as a tool for characterizing	
	nonequilibrium phase transitions"	
	Physical Review E <b>100</b> (1), 012104	2019

DECEMBER 28, 2022

JM Encinas, PE Harunari, MM de Oliveira, and CE Fiore, "Fundamental ingredients for discontinuous phase

transitions in the inertial majority vote model"

Scientific reports 8 (1), 1-9 PE Harunari, MM de Oliveira, and CE Fiore, "Partial inertia induces additional phase transition in the majority

vote model"

Physical Review E 96 (4), 042305 2017

## Work Experience

#### (Post)Modern Thermodynamics - School and workshop

Luxembourg, Luxembourg

Organizer

· Approximately, 100 participants from abroad and 30 from Luxembourg

- Conference consisting of 10 school lectures, 8 workshop sessions, and one poster session.
- · Shared teaching duties of the lecture "Continuous-time Markov chain: basics, first-passages and thermodynamics" with Ken Sekimoto.
- Co-organizers: Matteo Polettini, Vasco Cavina, William Piñeros.

#### The Abdus Salam International Centre for Theoretical Physics (ICTP)

Trieste, Italy

Dec 2022

2018

Visiting researcher

Visiting researcher

May 2022 - Jun 2022

Apr 2021 - Feb 2022

Visitor at Édgar Roldán's group.

**University of Luxembourg** 

Luxembourg, Luxembourg

• Visitor at Massimiliano Esposito's Complex Systems and Statistical Mechanics group.

· Supervised by Matteo Polettini.

**University of Aalto** Helsinki, Finland

Visiting researcher

Dec 2021 - Jan 2022

· Visitor at Jukka Pekola's PICO group.

#### The Abdus Salam International Centre for Theoretical Physics (ICTP)

Trieste, Italy

Visiting researcher

Jul 2021 - Sep 2021

· Visitor at Édgar Roldán's group.

#### **Statistical Physics seminar series**

online

Organizer

 21 seminars virtually presented during the COVID lockdown, mostly by professors, for a broad audience of students and researchers across Brazil and other countries. Co-organizer: Carlos E. Fiore.

University of São Paulo São Paulo, Brazil

Teaching assistant 2018 - 2020

Thermodynamics (2020);

- Statistical Mechanics (2018 and 2019);
- Graduate level Statistical Mechanics (2018).

University of São Paulo São Paulo, Brazil

Undergraduate researcher 2015 - 2017

Research training program.

• Supervisors: Mário J. de Oliveira (2015-2016), and Carlos E. Fiore (2016-2017).

## Skills\_\_\_\_\_

**Programming** Python, Mathematica, C.

Miscellaneous Usage of clusters, ETFX, Ubuntu Linux, teaching.

#### **Grants**

**FAPESP**, grant for 11 months of internship abroad (BEPE) 2021

2018 **FAPESP**, grant of 4 years for the Doctorate without Masters degree program

2017 FAPESP, grant for the Undergraduate research program

CNPq, grant for the Undergraduate research program 2016

DECEMBER 28, 2022

The 47th Conference of the Middle European Cooperation in Statistical Physics	Erice, Italy
MECO 47	2022
• <u>Poster</u> : "Inferences from Statistics of a Few Observable Transitions"	
Autumn meeting	São Paulo, Brazi
Brazilian Physical Society  Poster: "Inferences from Statistics of a Few Observable Transitions"	202.
National Statistical Physics Meeting	online
Universidade Federal de São João del-Rei (UFSJ)  Talk: "Inferences from Statistics of a Few Observable Transitions"	202.
Statistical Physics of Complex Systems	Trieste, Italj
The Abdus Salam International Centre for Theoretical Physics (ICTP)  Poster: "Entropy production fluctuation in phase transitions"	202.
Bangalore School on Statistical Physics XII nternational Center for Theoretical Sciences (ICTS)	online 202.
Autumn meeting	online
Brazilian Physical Society  Talk: "Entropy Production fluctuations in nonequilibrium transitions"	202.
Stochastic Thermodynamics II	online
Santa Fe Institute	202
APS March Meeting	online
American Physical Society  Talk: "Quantitative compartison of different time-periodic Thermodynamic Uncerainty Relations"	202.
Quantum Thermodynamics of Non-equilibrium systems	online
Donostia International Physics Center	202
Statistical Physics Seminar Series	online
University of São Paulo  Talk: "Stochastic Thermodynamics: Schnakenberg, FT and TUR"	202
Autumn meeting	online
Brazilian Physical Society	2020
• Talk: "Stochastic pump as a model to study nonequilibrium properties"	
Quantum Thermodynamics for Young Scientists	Bad Honnef, German
Wilhelm and Else Heraeus-Foundation	2020
<ul> <li>Poster: "Time assymetric reciprocity relations for an arbitrarily long single-particle stochastic pum</li> </ul>	
"Coloquinho" series of talks organized by IFT-UNESP, ICTP-SAIFR students	São Paulo, Brazi 201:
• Invited talk: "Stochastic Thermodynamics: basics and some modern aspects"	201
Physics Giants: Einstein Week	São Paulo, Brazi
series of talks organized by USP students	201:
Invited talk: "Einstein's contributions to Statistical Mechanics"	
Languages	

**Portuguese** Native proficiency

**Spanish** Llimited working proficiency

## Peer-review contributions \_\_\_\_\_

(3) Journal of Physics A: Mathematical and Theoretical, (1) Journal of Physics Communications

DECEMBER 28, 2022